Guide to the Ethelbert Nevin Collection, 1834-1980 CAM.NEV.1987.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Materials Related to the Ethelbert Nevin Room, XII.
  - Mitchell, Ruth Crawford to Nevin, Miss Doris, September 11, 1956 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1011)
  - Mitchell, Ruth Crawford to Van Dusen, A.C., July 17, 1958 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1012)
    typed copy of 6 page memorandum.
  - Oyen, Helen B. to Hodges, Jr., Fletcher, July 28, 1958 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1013)
  - Mitchell, Ruth Crawford to Fitzgerald, Dr., July 19th (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1014)
  - Peery, Rob Roy to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, June 26, 1937 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1015)
  - Peery, Rob Roy to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, July 16, 1937 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1016)
  - Robinson, A.L. to Finney, Theodore M., January 18, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1017)
  - Robison, A.L. to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, January 14, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1018)
    tls. Includes a copy of a proposal for the Nevin materials and a second, identical cover letter and proposal addressed to Theodore Finney.
  - Robinson, A.L. to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, January 18, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1019)
  - Robinson, A.L. to Finney, Theodore (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1020)
  - Rupp, G.S. to Schaefer, Frederic, January 3, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1021)
    photocopy of typed copy.
  - Rupp, G.S. to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, January 23, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1022)
  - Rupp, G.S. to Foster, W.K., September 22, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1023)
  - Hodges, Jr., Fletcher to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, July 24, 1958 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1024)
    tls and photocopy of tls.
  - Schaefer, Frederic to Bowman, John G., May 31, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1025)
  - Schroeder, Jean A. to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, January 14, 1953 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1026)
  - Shulgold, William R. to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, January 10, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1027)
  - Schirmer, Gustave to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, December 19, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1028)
  - Schirmer, Gustave to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, January 8, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1029)
  - Shook, Jr., Willis to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, November 12, 1938 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1030)
  - ??? to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, July 2, 1942 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1031)
  - Smith, Jeanne M. to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, October 5, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1032)
  - Chancellor's Office to Rupp, G.S., August 4, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1033)
  - Chancellor's office to Rupp, G.S., October 5, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1034)
  - Chancellor's office to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, March 2, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1035)
  - Chancellor's office to Howard, John Tasker, March 28, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1036)
  - Chancellor's office to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, August 16, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1037)
  - Chancellor's office to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, January 4, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1038)
  - Chancellor's office to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, Januar 16, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1039)
    Two typed copies.
  - Chancellor's office to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, January 6, 1936 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1040)
  - Chancellor's office to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, February 7, 1936 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1041)
  - Chancellor's office to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, December 2, 1936 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1042)
  - Chancellor's office to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, December 1, 1938 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1043)
  - Chancellor's office to Carnegie Book Shop, February 23, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1044)
  - Chancellor's office to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, March 7, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1045)
  - Stegeman, Mildred E. to Finney, Theodore M., January 7, 1960 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1046)
    typed copy and photocopy of typed copy.
  - Thompson, Mary Shaw to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, December 2, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1047)
    als with envelope.
  - Tucker, W.L. to Nevin, Miss Doris, November 28, 1956 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1048)
    Two typed copies and list entitled "University of Pittsburgh 45 Letters of Ethelbert Nevin presented to the University of Pittsburgh for the Nevin Collection by Miss Doris Nevin September, 1956."
  - ??? to Clapp, George H., May 25, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1049)
  - ??? to Howard, John Tasker, October 17, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1050)
  - ??? to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, January 22, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1051)
  - ??? to Dickson, Miss Elizabeth, January 30, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1052)
  - ??? to Dickson, Miss Elizabeth, December 23, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1053)
    typed copy. Includes a list dated Dec. 20, 1935 of materials in Dr. Linhart's safe.
  - ??? to Dickson, Elizabeth, July 28, 1938 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1054)
  - ??? to Nevin, Mrs. Ethelbert, August 4, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1055)
    typed copy plus notated draft.
  - Mitchell, Ruth Crawford to Witman, Dr. Shepherd (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1056)
    two typed copies
  - Witman, Shepherd to Mitchell, Ruth Crawford, October 22, 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1057)
    photocopy of typed memo.
  - List of materials prepared by Mrs. Ethelbert Nevin, October 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1058)
  - Brief biographical bullet points of Ethelbert Nevin's life (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1059)
  - Timeline for the development of the Ethelbert Nevin Collection (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1060)
  - Partial list of materials in the Ethelbert Nevin Collection (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1061)
  - Floorplan for the Ethelbert Nevin Room, November 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1062)
  - General Exhibit Neviniana Gifts of Mrs. Nevin as Revised by Mrs. Nevin, November 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1063)
  - Memorandum on Working with Anne Nevin on the Ethelbert Nevin Memorial, June 21, 1950 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1064)
  - List of Framed Mementoes Arcady, September 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1065)
  - Ethelbert Nevin Collection Master List, November 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1066)
    Bound in gray folder; Prepared April and November 1959 by Ruth Crawford Mitchell
  - Ethelbert Nevin Collection Masterlist, 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1067)
    bound hard cover copy with note to Dr. Shepherd Witman tipped in. Catalogued copy (since removed).
  - Draft of Ethelbert Nevin Collection Masterlist, November 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1068)
    photocopy of list with corrections.
  - Incomplete copy of Ethelbert Nevin Collection Masterlist, November 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1069)
  - Meeting of January 4, 1952, Concerned with the Nevin Project (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1070)
  - Scheme No. 1 Blueprint of the Proposed Ethelbert Nevin Memorial 3034, April 3, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1071)
  - Scheme No. 1 Blueprint of the Proposed Ethelbert Nevin Memorial 3034A, April 3, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1072)
  - List of Studio Furnishings Original pieces to be given by Mrs. Nevin, July 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1073)
  - Ethelbert Nevin Archives Notes on Conference with Professor Finney, February 18, 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1074)
  - Photostat of the cover of "The Rosary" by Ethelbert Nevin (Boston Music Co, 1900) (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1075)
    includes copy of the form requesting the photostat from the Cleveland Public Library.
  - Notes about "The Rosary" given by Miss Elizabeth Dickson to Mrs. Ruth Crawford Mitchell, April 1937 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1076)
  - Outline of the Plan for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial as conceived with Anne Paul Nevin at "Arcady", July 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1077)
  - Material in the Nevin Collection, University of Pittsburgh, Studied January - February, 1940 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1078)
  - List of Works (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1079)
  - Ethelbert Nevin Memorial Material, May 16, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1080)
  - Synopsis - Life of Ethelbert Nevin (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1081)
  - Chief Donors to Nevin Collection at the University of Pittsburgh, March 19, 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1082)
  - Pencil sketch of Narcissus Presented to Mrs. Nevin by Daniel Gregory Mason for Nevin Memorial (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1083)
    typed description of sketch -- NOT image of actual sketch.
  - Nevin Collection Memorandum, October 18, 1950 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1084)
    Handwritten notation from Dec. 18, 1951 at bottom of page.
  - Memorandum Nevin Memorial Conversations with Doris Nevin by Telephone April 19 and 20, 1956 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1085)
  - Clues for Additional Materials from Anne Paul Nevin, April 10-14, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1086)
  - Notes regarding Doris Nevin's visit to the University, June 21, 1950 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1087)
    Includes handwritten additions from November 21, 1951, and December 1951.
  - Points that might be made in talking with Miss Nevin, November 21, 1951 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1089)
  - Hurried Notes on the Start of the Nevin Collection at the University of Pittsburgh 1933, March 18, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1090)
  - Proposal for Ethelbert Nevin calendar, 1951 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1091)
  - Rendell, Diana J. to Stephens, Norris, May 23, 1974 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1092)
    Letter from Ethelbert Nevin to Elizabeth Dickson dated March 23, 1891 on sale from a manuscript dealer (photocopy enclosed).
  - List of Material presented to University by Mrs. Nevin, selected by Ruth Crawford Mitchell, July 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1093)
  - List of boxes received from Mrs. Nevin, October 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1094)
  - List of material presented to the University by Mrs. Nevin, January 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1095)
  - List of Mementos presented to the University by Miss Eizabeth Dickson, April 2, 1937 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1096)
  - List of Gifts presented to the University of Pittsburgh by Dr. Arthur Nevin, December, 1938 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1097)
  - List of Material Presented to the University of Pittsburgh for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial by Miss Elizabeth Dickson, 1935List of Material Presented to the University of Pittsburgh for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial by Miss Elizabeth Dickson (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1098)
  - Material received from Mrs. Nevin on October 16, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1099)
  - Framed manuscript Christmas Song 1887 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1100)
    typed descirption of manuscript and who had copies in their possession.
  - List of Manuscripts sent to University of Pittsburgh as listed in Mrs. Nevin's letter of May 1, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1101)
  - List of manuscripts Ethelbert Nevin Arcady, July 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1102)
  - List of Ethelbert Nevin's Manuscripts REceived January 10, 1934 from Mrs. Nevin (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1103)
  - List of Twenty Nevin manuscripts purchased by Frederic Schaefer for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial, University of Pittsburgh, December 7, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1104)
  - List of Manuscripts returned to Mrs. Nevin, September, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1105)
  - Manuscripts of works by Ethelbert Nevin offered by Mrs. Nevin to the University of Pittsburgh, November 5, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1106)
  - List of twenty-two Ethelbert Nevin Manuscripts purchased by the University of Pittsburgh, January 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1107)
  - Manuscript Works by Ethelbert Nevin Purchased by the University of Pittsburgh from Mrs. Nevin, January 19, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1108)
  - Original Nevin Manuscripts at Arcady, September 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1109)
  - List of 16 Ethelbert Nevin Manuscripts presented by Mrs. Nevin and her friends to the University of Pittsburgh for the Ethelbert Nevin Memorial Room, April 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1110)
  - List of twenty Nevin manuscripts purchased by Frederick Schaefer for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial, University of Pittsburgh, April 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1111)
  - List of 22 Manuscript works by Ethelbert Nevin received from Mrs. Nevin by the University, January, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1112)
  - List of 24 Manuscript works purchased from Mrs. Nevin by the University, January, 1935 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1113)
  - List of Manuscript Material presented to the University of Pittsburgh for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial presented by Miss Elizabeth Dickson, 1935, April 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1114)
  - List of twenty Nevin manuscripts purchased by Frederic Schaefer for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial, University of Pittsburgh (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1115)
  - Original manuscripts presented to the University of Pittsburgh by Mrs. Nevin, March 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1116)
  - List of Ethelbert Nevin's Manuscripts presented by Mrs. Nevin and Her friedns to the University of Pittsburgh for the Ethelbert Nevin Memorial Room, March 20, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1117)
  - List of Manuscripts in Custody of the University not yet purchased (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1118)
  - List of Ethelbert Nevin's Manuscripts taken to Mr. Rupp's Office to be put in the safe, December 6, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1119)
  - 45 Letters of Ethelbert Nevin presented to the University of Pittsburgh for the Nevin Collection by Miss Doris Nevin, September 1956 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1120)
  - General Collection of letters written by Ethelbert W. Nevin (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1121)
  - List suggested by Miss Dickson for Ethelbert Nevin Memorial Committee (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1122)
  - Inventory of Furnishings in Studio of Ethelbert nevin at Queen Anne's Lodge Sewickely 1898 presented to the University of Pittsburgh for the Ethelbert Nevin Memorial, November 17, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1123)
  - Contents of Boxes Containing Nevin Furniture in Storeroom, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1124)
  - Articles & Clippings, January 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1125)
  - Clippings, January 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1126)
  - List of articles displayed at the Presbyterian Church House, Sewickley Pennsylvania, in connection with a program of Ethelbert Nevin's music presented by the choral of the Sewickley Music Club, March 19, 1938 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1127)
  - The Ethelbert Nevin Memorial in the University of Pittsburgh Printed Music, Books, May, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1128)
  - The Ethelbert Nevin Memorial in the University of Pittsburgh, Printed music, books, 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1129)
  - List of Ethelbert Nevin Printed Music and Books presented by Mrs. Nevin to the University of Pittsburgh, March 1939 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1130)
  - List of Selected items from the University of Pittsburgh's large collection of Ethelbert Nevin materials, borrowed by the Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania, April 10, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1131)
  - Freight bill for charges from the Pennsylvania Railroad Company, October 13, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1132)
  - University of Pittsburgh Cafeteria Receipt, December 4, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1133)
  - Receipt acknowledging receipt, by messenger, of Nevin manuscripts, January 29, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1134)
  - Receipt for crating and sending Nevin furniture, March 6, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1135)
  - Invoice for crating and sending Nevin furniture, March 7, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1136)
  - Receipt for two Nevin diaries received by Ruth Crawford Mitchell, March 28, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1137)
  - Receipt from John Tasker Howard acknowledging receipt of Nevin Diaries from Chancellor Bowman, March 30, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1138)
  - Receipt from John Tasker Howard acknowledging receiving Nevin press clippings, articles, programs, and book from Nevin collection, June 25, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1139)
  - Receipt of Forbes National Bank for Package left in their care of Nevin Manuscripts, December 4, 1934 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1140)
  - Receipt from Theodore Finney acknowledging receiving Nevin manuscripts from Ruth Crawford Mitchell, October 2, 1951 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1141)
  - Receipt acknowledging that Fletcher Hodges, Jr., has accepted Nevin manuscripts for deposit at Foster Memorial, October 21, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1142)
  - Receipt acknowledging transfer of sealed package of Nevin Material from the Foster Memorial to the Music Library, November 11, 1959 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1143)
  - Unidentified notes (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1144)
  - Unidentified list of names and numbers (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1145)
  - Unidentified notes (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1146)
  - Dr. Clapp correspondence with Mrs. Nevin before May, 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1147)
  - Nevin Material brought back from New York, November 1933 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1148)
  - The Ethelbert Nevin Collection at the U of P talk before the Sewickley Musical Club, January 15, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1149)
  - Photograph of a list of an unidentified list of names (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1150)
  - Meeting of January 4, 1952, Concerned with the Nevin Project (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1151)
  - Certification that the Nevin manuscripts are not part of the Foster Hall Collection, October 21, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1152)
  - Letter from Fletcher Hodges, Jr. to Ruth Crawford Mitchell re package of Nevin material stored in the Foster Memorial safe, July 24, 1958 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1153)
  - Correspondence from Walter Read Hovey to Dr. R.H. Fitzgerald re storing Nevin manuscripts in the Foster Memorial safe, October 1, 1952 (File-cabinet 19, Drawer 2, Folder 1154)
- Furniture, XIII.
  - A Cradle, 1.
  - A Spinning Wheel, 2.
  - Bed, 3.
  - Unknown
    Unspecified location. TL: Incomplete. First line: "... the world, three quarters of it is mine to do what I please with..." Missing